<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An account of the ceremony of investing his Electoral Highness of Brandenburgh; with the Order of the Garter Perform'd at Berlin on the 6th of June, 1690. By James Johnston Esq; His Majesties envoy extraordinary to his Electoral Highness, and principal commissioner. And Gregory King, Esq; the other commissioner for this investiture. With the speeches made at this solemnity by the said Mr. Johnston, and Monsieur Fulks, minister of state to his Electoral Highness.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A24989</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A262</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R214305</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99826499</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99826499</idno>
            <idno type="VID">30902</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A24989)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 30902)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1841:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An account of the ceremony of investing his Electoral Highness of Brandenburgh; with the Order of the Garter Perform'd at Berlin on the 6th of June, 1690. By James Johnston Esq; His Majesties envoy extraordinary to his Electoral Highness, and principal commissioner. And Gregory King, Esq; the other commissioner for this investiture. With the speeches made at this solemnity by the said Mr. Johnston, and Monsieur Fulks, minister of state to his Electoral Highness.</title>
                  <author>King, Gregory, 1648-1712.</author>
                  <author>Johnston, James, 1655-1737.</author>
                  <author>Fuchs, Paul von, 1640-1704.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed at London and re-printed at Edinburgh, by the heir of Andrew Anderson, printer to their most excellent Majesties,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[[Edinburgh] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>The speech of Fuchs is given in English in parallel columns with the Latin.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Frederick --  I, --  King of Prussia, 1657-1713 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Order of the Garter --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:30902:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>AN ACCOUNT OF THE CEREMONY OF INVESTING His ELECTORAL HIGHNESS OF <hi>BRANDENB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH;</hi> WITH THE Order of the Garter. PERFORM'D <hi>At</hi> Berlin <hi>on the</hi> 6th <hi>of</hi> June, 1690.</head>
            <head type="sub">By <hi>James Johnſton</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> His Majeſties Envoy extraordinary to His Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoral Highneſs, and Principal Commiſſioner. And <hi>Gregory King</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> the other Commiſſioner for this Inveſtiture. With the Speeches made at this Solemnity by the ſaid Mr. <hi>Johnſton,</hi> and Monſieur <hi>Fulks,</hi> Miniſter of State to his Electoral Highneſs.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E arrived here on <hi>Tueſday</hi> the 27th of <hi>May, Old ſtile,</hi> with Mr. <hi>Johnſton,</hi> His Majeſties Envoy extraordinary; and Mr. <hi>King,</hi> Commiſſioner for the Inveſtiture. The The Elector came hither Poſt on the <hi>Saturday</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, from <hi>Coningsberg.</hi> On <hi>Monday</hi> following, being the ſecond of <hi>June,</hi> the Commiſſioners had a privat Audience; at which they delivered the Credential Letters and Book of Statutes; after which they put on the Elector the <hi>Ribbon-Garter</hi> and <hi>George.</hi> —They had likewiſe a privat Audience
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:30902:2"/>of Her Electoral Highneſs, of the Princeſs Electreſs, and of the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graff,</hi> and two other Princes, the Elector's Brothers. This they did for the diſpatch, and that they might have the freedom of going to Court, and ſeing the adjuſting of the States, and the putting of all other things in Order, againſt the time of the Solemn Inveſtiture. But they could not have a publick Audience, nor could the Ceremony of Inveſtiture be performed, till the Elector's Court, and his Coaches and Horſes ſhould arrive; which hapned on <hi>Thurſday</hi> night. In the mean time all other things were made ready, and the next day, being <hi>Friday</hi> the 6th of <hi>June,</hi> was appointed both for the publick Audience, and the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Inveſtiture. The Commiſſioners were willing that theſe two ſhould be joined together, that no time might be loſt, nor the Elector's Journey to the <hi>Rhine</hi> ſtopt ſo much as one moment, upon the account of the Solemnity.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Friday</hi> morning the Baron of <hi>Shiarm,</hi> the eldeſt Privy Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, or Miniſter of State (as they ſpeak here) came from Court, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with a great many other Gentlemen, and particularly with Monſieur <hi>Beſcat,</hi> (whoſe Office it was to regulat the Ceremony) all in Rich Cloaths, with ſix of the Elector's Coaches, and ſix Horſes in each of them, and carried the Commiſſioners and their Retinue to Court; twenty four <hi>Trabants,</hi> or Horſe-Guards, walking along all the way on both ſides of the Coaches: Not to mention a great many of the Elector's Servants that did alſo attend them. At Court they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived with Double Guards, and Colours Diſplayed, Twenty four Trumpets, and two pair of Kettle-Drums ſounding all the while. The Commiſſioners Coach paſſed through the Inner-Court of the Caſtle; at the foot of the Stairs the Commiſſioners were received by the Grand Marſhal, with his Silver Staff of Office: At the head of the Stairs they were met by the Elector's Great Chamberlain, the Count of <hi>Denherff,</hi> and ſo were conducted to the Elector's Chamber; all the Rooms, as they paſs along, being full of the Nobility and Gentry of the Court, and the <hi>Trebants</hi> making the Guard up the Stairs, and along the two firſt Rooms.</p>
            <p>From the Elector's Apartment, they went to an Audience of the Electrice, where were all the Princes and Princeſſes of the Family, and the Ladies of the Court, richly dreſſed: Then they were conducted to the Rooms where the Robes of Order were before placed, where all
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:30902:2"/>things being in readineſs, they went to another Room near adjoining, in which his Electoral Highneſs was, and thence began the Proceſſion to the Great Hall, which is one of the nobleſt Rooms that is to be ſeen any where, being above 100 foot long, and above 50 foot broad, adorn'd all about with the Marble Statues of the Electors of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, and the Roof richly painted. They went in this Order: Firſt, The Nobility and Officers of the Court in great number; The Grand Marſhal and Marſhal with their Silver Staves of Office, being the laſt of them. Next came two belonging to the Commiſſioners, one of them carrying the King's Commiſſion, and the other the Cap and Feather; then followed Mr. <hi>Gregory King</hi> in the Mantle of the Kings at Arms, bearing the Habit and Enſigns of the Order on a Velvet Cuſhion. Next came Mr. <hi>Johnſton</hi> alone; and in the laſt place his Electoral Highneſs, attended by the Prince of <hi>Anhalt,</hi> and the Grand Chamberlain.</p>
            <p>Thus they went through a long Gallery (having the <hi>Trabants</hi> on each ſide) into the Hall, and ſo into the Rails which divided the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per end of the Hall, that was raiſed four Steps, making the due Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verences to the Soveraign's State; the Electrice, with the Princeſſes and Princes Ladies, and publick Miniſters, having before taken their places within the Rails.</p>
            <p>The Elector being placed under his State, and the Robes being laid on a Table near his Highneſs, the two Commiſſioners ſeated themſelves in two armed Chairs, and the Trumpets and Muſick ceaſing, <hi>Mr. Johnſton</hi> made a Diſcourſe in <hi>Engliſh.</hi> But not to oblige the Elector to ſtand, becauſe of an hurt in his Leg, the Expedient fallen upon was this; That in ſtead of four Diſcourſes (as the Cuſtom is) two by one of the Commiſſioners, and two by one belonging to the Elector; that one only ſhould be made by Mr. <hi>Johnſton</hi> in the beginning, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at the end of the Ceremony by Monſieur <hi>Fulks,</hi> one of the Elector's Miniſters of State. And therefore Mr. <hi>Johnſton</hi> having put his two Diſcourſes into one, and having only told the ſubſtance of them in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh, he preſented a Tranſlation in <hi>High Dutch</hi> to the Elector, which he ordered his Chief Secretary to read; the Elector and the Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners having ſtood during the pronouncing of the Engliſh, but ſitting when the Dutch Copy was read. Then they preſented the King's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the Elector, which he gave to a Miniſter of ſtate, who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it to the Secretary to be read, the Elector and all others ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:30902:3"/>up; which being again delivered to the Elector, his Highneſs gave it to Mr. <hi>King;</hi> After which, the Commiſſioners having taken off his Highneſs'<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Coat, Sword, Belt, Ribbon George and Garter, Mr. <hi>John<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ston</hi> inveſted the Elector with the Diamond Garter, the Surcoat, the Sword and Belt, the great Mantle, the Hood, and at laſt the great Collar and George, in the order as they were delivered to him by Mr. <hi>King;</hi> who pronounced in Latin the uſual Forms of Admonitions u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon Mr. <hi>Johnston's</hi> putting on the Elector each Enſign. Then they preſented to his Electoral Highneſs the Book of Statutes under the great Seal of the Order, and he delivered them Letters certifying his recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Order, and containing an Engagement to obſerve the Statutes with the uſual Exceptions. Theſe Letters had already his Sign, and Seal at them, yet his Electoral Highneſs had a Pen given him, and he made a ſhew of writing his Name.</p>
            <p>Next they preſented him with the Cap and Feather, which his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectoral Highneſs had enriched with Diamonds to the value of above 50000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> one of the ſtones coſt above 10000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>Then Mr. <hi>King</hi> did congratulate his Electoral Highneſs, and proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the Soveraigns and New-Knights Titles, upon which the Trumpets ſounded, and the Drums beat, and Muſick play'd.</p>
            <p>This being over, Mr. <hi>Johnſton</hi> did alſo congratulate his Highneſs in in a ſhort Complement, and then Monſieur <hi>Fulks</hi> made an handſome Speech to the praiſe of the Soveraign and the Order. This Speech was in <hi>High-Dutch,</hi> that it might be underſtood by the whole Aſſembly; and a Copy of it being given to Mr. <hi>Stepney,</hi> Mr. <hi>Johnston</hi>'s Secretary, he read it publickly, the Elector and Commiſſioners ſitting all the while that Monſieur <hi>Fulks</hi> ſpoke, and that the Copy was read. Then they preſented the Stars or Glories, and the Riboon of the Order; and returning to their Chairs, the Drums beat, the Trumpets ſounded, and the Cannon round the Town was thrice diſcharged. Then the Elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or and Commiſſioners returned in proceſſion as they came, and Mr. <hi>Norton,</hi> Collonel <hi>Norton</hi>'s Grandſon, he had the honour to carry the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector's Train.</p>
            <p>A little after this, they came back to the Hall again to Dinner, where his Electoral Highneſs and the two Commiſſioners only did ſit at the Table, his Highneſs being in the Robes, and the Court attending: The Elector began firſt the King's Health; 2dly, the Queen's; 3dly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:30902:3"/>Knights of the Order; 4thly, Proſperity to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation; 5thly, Succeſs to the Campaign. Mr. <hi>Johnston</hi> began firſt the Elector's Health; 2dly, the Electorices; 3dly, the Electoral Families; the Elector and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners ſtood up, and the Guns were diſcharged at every Glaſs. After Dinner the Commiſſioners were carried home in the ſame manner as they were brought in the morning; at night they returned to Court in two Coaches with ſix Horſes, and ſupp'd with the Elector, the Electrice, and the Princeſs, where many of the ſame Healths were drunk again with the ſame Ceremony of firing, and ſtanding up.</p>
            <p>After supper the Fire-works began, and were much admired by eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one, conſidering they had only three days to prepare them: There were many Rockets of all ſorts, and four great Fire-works of 40 or 50 foot high, the chief burnt blew, and was compoſed of the repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Garter, having within it theſe four Letters, <hi>V. W. M. R.</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying <hi>Vivant Willielmus Maria Reges;</hi> and without the Garter were the ſupporting Crown and Creſt of <hi>England.</hi> The other three were Pyramids burning in bright white fire, with Crowns on the tops of them; the middlemoſt having the Letter B. and the other two, <hi>F.</hi> and <hi>H.</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying <hi>Britannia, Francia, Hibernia.</hi> The Elector hath ordered the Garter to be put on the Plate. Ever ſince the publick Audience, we have been entertained at our Lodgings at the Elector's charge, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by his Officers. Both the Commiſſioners have received Rich Preſents, the principal Commiſſioners being double the value of what was given to the other. The Servants of the firſt, to the number of 16, and thoſe of the other Commiſſioner, 3, had all conſiderable Preſents according to their ſeveral Offices. In a word, every thing was done for the honour of the Soveraign of it, and of the new Knight; and in a manner more noble than it could have been expected the ſhortneſs of time would have allow'd.</p>
            <div type="speech">
               <head>
                  <hi>Mr. Johnſton's</hi> Speech to his Electoral Highneſs.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>May it pleaſe Your Electoral Highneſs,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>NOthing excites in men the deſire of Glory ſo much as ſignal and laſting marks of Honour. For to Noble and Generous Minds, Honour is certainly the greateſt Reward, and ſuch marks are the moſt acceptable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of it to wit, a publick acknowledgment that men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:30902:4"/>
Of theſe marks, the moſt eminent have been appropriated to Chevalry. Religion hath its Treaſury above. Juſtice, and the other peaceable Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues without Arms, would be of little or no uſe. Therefore Military Glory, as moſt neceſſary, hath been preferr'd to all others; beſides, it is acquired with greater danger, and is founded on nobler Paſſions.</p>
               <p>Amongſt all incitements to it, nothing hath proved ſo effectual as the Inſtitution of the Orders of Knights, Companions and Brethren.</p>
               <p>Such Orders do engage Princes by the ſtricteſt Ties of Honour, to give in their own Perſons an example of Military Virtue, as alſo the higheſt Incouragement imaginable to follow it: For by theſe Fraterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties they deſcend from their Greatneſs, and conſent, that brave and gallant Men ſhould be brought into a ſort of Equality with themſelves.</p>
               <p>Amongſt Military Orders, there are none that can diſpute either An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity or Dignity with that of the Garter; which may indeed be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Mother Order, For the other great Orders have ſprung out of this Root, being formed upon the Model of it.</p>
               <p>Such Inſtitutions, like other things of the ſame nature, in their firſt conceptions uſe to be imperfect, and calculated for receiving the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations that time only brings: But the Rules of this Order were from the beginning ſo well digeſted, that they have admitted of few or no material Changes.</p>
               <p>To the Antiquity and Wiſdom of the Inſtitution, <hi>I</hi> may add the Chaſtity of the Order: The Knights have at no time exceeded the firſt foundation of Twenty ſix, contrary to the fate of other Orders, of which none have ſupported their Dignity as this hath done, conſidering joint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſmal number, and ſingular eminency of thoſe that have been of it, <hi>viz.</hi> Four hundred ninty ſeven only. And yet amongſt theſe, there have been eight Emperors (of whom two, <hi>Sigiſmond,</hi> and <hi>Charles</hi> the Vth went to <hi>England</hi> and received it there, ſo much did they value the Honour of being of it;) Forty five Kings, including thoſe of <hi>England;</hi> and above ſixty Princes, for the moſt part Soveraigns; Not to mention that the others generally deſerving to be Princes, were therefore by the Order in a manner made ſuch.</p>
               <p>The Qualities of <hi>Edward</hi> III. who founded this Order, gave a pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Luſtre to it; He was the Greateſt and Braveſt Prince of his Time, in the opinion of all others, as well as of the <hi>Germans,</hi> who firſt made Him Vicar-General of the Empire, and afterwards offered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> perial Diadem.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:30902:4"/>
He claimed the Crown of <hi>France</hi> as his Juſt and Lawful Inheritance, and ſtudied by the Inſtitution of this Order, to engage the moſt mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Spirits of the Age, in his Quarrel. It was with his Garter that he gave the Signal at the Battel of <hi>Creſſey;</hi> remembering, it ſeems, that which was reported of one of his Predeceſſors, <hi>Richard</hi> the 1ſt, That he had upon a like occaſion, with great Succeſs, made uſe of a Garter. In this Battel the whole Power of <hi>France</hi> fell before Him; upon which Augury he made the Garter the chief Sign of the Order. <hi>Richard</hi> the 1st, is alſo ſaid upon ſuch an account to have had the ſame deſign. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, a Garter is the Symbol and Badg of Unity, and therefore moſt proper to ſignifie theſe Bonds of Amity and Affection, into which all the Companions were to reckon themſelves knit.</p>
               <p>He delighted much in Devices, and choſe for the Device of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, theſe words, <hi>Honi ſoit qui mal y Penſe;</hi> in <hi>Engliſh, May he be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed that thinks ill</hi> (or does not approve) <hi>of it.</hi> That is, either of the Order it ſelf, or of his Title to the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> which gave occaſion to the Inſtitution.</p>
               <p>He made <hi>Blew</hi> the chief Colour, that being the Colour of the Field of the Arms of <hi>France,</hi> which, with the Title he had about that time aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed to himſelf, his Succeſſors have ever ſince uſed: Beſides, <hi>Blew</hi> denotes the Sublime and Celeſtial Temper of thoſe who were to be of the Order. The Pilgrims that returned from the <hi>Holy Land,</hi> brought over ſuch an account of St. <hi>George</hi> (then the <hi>Chriſtian Mars</hi>) particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly of his Tutelary care of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in that War, that according to the Perſuaſions of thoſe Times, he made him the Patron of the Order, as well as of the Nation.</p>
               <p>He wiſely conſidered that other Sovereign Princes might think it a leſſening of them, to come into an Order ſubject to the Laws and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of <hi>England;</hi> therefore he intirely ſeparated its Concerns, and made it a diſtinct Body with Seals and Officers, and Statutes peculiar to it; over which the Seals and Laws of <hi>England</hi> have no ſort of Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
               <p>This is the Order, <hi>Sir,</hi> ſo deſervedly famous over all Chriſtendom, theſe Three hundred and forty Years, of which we have now the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, in the Name of the King our Maſter, to Preſent Your Electoral Highneſs the Enſigns. The ſame Order which His Highneſs, Your Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Father, deſired ſo much, and received as a great Honour done
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:30902:5"/>him, and to which he did great Honour: He wore it in a time of Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when the Fate not only of the <hi>North,</hi> but of the whole Empire; nay, I may add, of all <hi>Europe,</hi> turned according to the Meaſures that he took, and which is more, turned often with the approbation of all good men. It was thus that he run his Career, which he finiſhed with an happineſs that might be called <hi>the obtaining of the Prize,</hi> if that were to be done here; For he being full of Honour and Years, in Peace and Quiet, Belov'd and Eſteem'd by the better part of Mankind, died; leaving behind him the only Two things to be left, a Great and Good Name, and a Glorious Succeſſor.</p>
               <p>It is alſo the ſame Garter, as well as the ſame Order, with which we are to inveſt your Highneſs. This I ſhould call a happy <hi>Omen,</hi> that the Order is ſtill to receive the ſame Honour: But your Highneſs hath not left the World to Divination and Conjecture; you have begun your Regence in a way worthy of the Son of ſuch a Father, and already given Mankind real inſtances of that which they may expect: And now this day you are to put the Order in poſſeſſion of the Honour which you have, as it were, advanced to it, and to which the Order hath a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Claim, your Highneſs having acquired the ſame, as the Founder did his, by defeating the acient Enemies of both Nations. For this Reaſon, I ſuppoſe, the King, my Maſter, as well as for doing your Highneſs greater Honour, hath ſent you a Sword, amongſt the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of the Order, which hitherto was never done to any other.</p>
               <p>Sir, Nothing is more evident than that this Society was inſtituted for carrying on a War with <hi>France,</hi> in which War, the Emperor, the Princes of <hi>Brandenburg, Bavaria, Lorrain,</hi> and many others, were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged by a Confederacy with the Founder of this Order, as your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and others, their Succeſſors, are now with the preſent Soveraign of it. It ſeems in all Ages it hath been the Wiſdom of Great Princes to have no other thing to do with that Crown. Sure that which hath hapned in this Age, doth not alter the Caſe; nay, the preſent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacy is a Demonſtration, that it is the Senſe of Mankind, that the Publick quiet can be no longer ſecured by the Faith of Treaties; and therefore, that a firm Peace is only to be obtained by a thorough War: For Men that having enriched themſelves by Violence, are fallen in love with it, will love on till they loſe by it, then it will be ſeaſonable. To truſt to Treaties, the incapacity ſuch Men ſhall be in to break them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:30902:5"/>
                  <hi>Edward</hi> the 3d deſigned a Conqueſt, and ſucceeded in it: But there is here place for yet a more Noble Deſign, that of a Redemption. The Work of an <hi>Hero</hi> is not to mind his own Buſineſs only, much leſs to do hurt, to plunder the World with <hi>Alexander,</hi> or ruine his own Countrey with <hi>Caeſar;</hi> but to do good chiefly to others; to chain up the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbers of the Publick Peace, to ſet Bounds to Exorbitant Power, and the Will of Man; <hi>and ſo to deſerve the Bleſſings of thoſe that were ready to periſh. All this the King, my Maſter, hath done, by redeeming his own Countrey from Ruine, and other Countreys from the danger of it,</hi> in ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to become his own: <hi>Thus endeavouring every where to ſtem the Inundations of the preſent Times, as his Ancestors did thoſe of theirs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to this, not only the Example of the Soveraign invites thoſe of the Order, but the Order it ſelf, in a particular manner, engages them, <hi>Pugnare pro jure &amp; tuitione oppreſſorum &amp; indigentium,</hi> To fight for the relief of the poor and the oppreſſed.</p>
               <p>This, Reaſon, Humanity, common Chriſtianity, and Intereſt too, requires of all Men, much more of Princes, that are to act as Gods Vicegerents, who Glories in nothing oftner than in his firm purpoſes to avenge and Protect Widows and Orphans, and ſuch others, the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, though Unfortunate part of Mankind, to wit, by commanding all thoſe that have power to do it, to puniſh their Oppreſſors.</p>
               <p>Thus it is here, That a Capacity to do good, not only gives a Title to it, but makes the doing of it a Duty. It is ſtrange, That among Chriſtians in all Times there ſhould have been ſome who doubted of this, and have had narrower Thoughts of Heroical Enterprizes than either the <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Heathens</hi> had; nay, of whom ſome have believ'd all War to be unlawful, ſince the Deſign of Chriſtianity was to exalt our Natures to a higher and ſublimer pitch of Perfection, and not to ſtifle and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, with ſpecious pretences, that which is moſt Commendable in them, the Inclinations and Ties we may have to do one another good.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Jews</hi> of old had ſo Noble an Opinion of ſuch Performances, that they imputed them to Inſpiration; they thought, that without extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Aſſiſtances, Men had neither Goodneſs nor Largeneſs of Soul ſufficient for them.</p>
               <p>It is true, ſeveral among them endeavoured thus to defend the Irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larities that ſometimes did accompany ſuch Actions, and ſuppoſed an expreſs Order from God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as neceſſary to juſtifie them. Yet Rules and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:30902:6"/>Laws are means for obtaining the ends which they relate to, and in that relation cannot be too well obſerved; but they are not the ends them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves which muſt ſtill be purſued, tho in another way, if the ordinary way fails. No doubt the Letter of the Law, that upon great occaſions oppoſes it ſelf to the publick Safety, which is intended by all Laws, muſt needs be the Letter that kills. This thoſe high Pretenders came at laſt to underſtand (and to fight even on their <hi>Sabbaths</hi>) tho their Laws were given them by God; and that it was their humour to ſwallow Camels, and ſtrain at Gnats; to let go the Subſtance for the Law, and periſh in defence of the Letter of it. The true ſtanding Character in all Ages and Nations, and ordinarly the Fate too, of Weak, and Warm, and Obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate (tho often Well meaning) Men.</p>
               <p>Thoſe <hi>Jews</hi> are much more in the right, who aſcribe great Events more particularly to God, becauſe of that which is ſingular (as well as of his Concern) in them. Thus they would, no doubt, judge of the late Revolution in <hi>Britain,</hi> where we have an Illuſtrious Example of ſuch ſorts of Events. In which the concurrence of great Dangers, of an unexpected Opportunity to be delivered from them; of the Capacity and Circumſtances of the Deliverer, as if they had been given for this End; of the evident infatuation of thoſe, whoſe Intereſt (and in whoſe Power) it was to have prevented it; of a multitude of meer Accidents previous and abſolutly neceſſary to it, which by Humane Wiſdom could neither have been forſeen nor procured: In aword, of a Chain and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>incidency of various, and often, in appearance Croſs Events, yet in effect, ſo well agreeing with the Methods reſolved on, that Divine Goodneſs and Humane Prudence ſeem to have had a Correſpendence. All this, with the ſudden vaniſhing of Difficulties that had appear'd, in a manner inſuperable, and a Succeſs worthy of the Care of Providence (ſuch as Hiſtory cannot parallel) without Blood, Danger, or Diſorder; So <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Publick Peace and Quiet ſeemed rather not interrupted than reſtored; as if no change had hapned, except in our Hearts and Thoughts. All this I ſay, does compleat an Event ſo much above the ordinary courſe of things, that whoever believes, that God does at all concern himſelf in Humane Affairs (much more ſuch as believe, that the Hairs of our Heads are numbred), muſt needs conclude, that this whole buſineſs was (to ſpeak ſo) laid and concerted by him. <hi>Sed praeſtat de Cartha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, ut aiunt, ſilere quam pauca dicere.</hi> And therefore to return to my Subject.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:30902:6"/>
The <hi>Heathens</hi> went yet further in doing Honour to the Authors of ſuch great Undertakings; They thought they could not do too much to encourage Men to venture upon them: And therefore upon ſuch ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts they Defied their <hi>Hero's;</hi> Men ſeemed to them in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance ſo like their Gods, that they could not abſtain from Honouring the Copies with the Names of the Originals. The <hi>Heathens</hi> conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Publick Good that was done; for as their <hi>Hero's</hi> became their Gods for chaſtiſing Oppreſſors, in their Opinions the Enemies of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, ſo others became their <hi>Hero's</hi> for deſtroying Monſtrous Beaſts of the ſame Temper, if we may not rather believe, as no doubt we may, that the Poets, the Hiſtorians of thoſe Times, meant Men (and to them gave the other borrowed Name, as more proper than their own) whoſe Souls, by Succeſs in their Paſſions, were become as Monſtrous as they deſcrib'd the Shapes and Voracity of thoſe Beaſts to have been.</p>
               <p>Sir, How great and noble Thoughts would thoſe <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> have of the preſent Undertaking in which the King, my Maſter, your Electoral Highneſs, and ſo many other Princes are engaged? An Undertaking ſuch as Humane Nature requires, where Honour, and Duty, and Intereſt go hand in hand together: And the moſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing to be done, is the greateſt and beſt thing that can be done.</p>
               <p>In particular, it is an Undertaking that will tranſmit your Highneſs Name glorious to Poſterity: for you firſt gave life and motion to it, by ſaving the Town of <hi>Cullen,</hi> and that whole Electorat, by taking <hi>Keiſerſwert, Rhinberg</hi> and <hi>Bonn;</hi> by routing the Forces ſent to aſſiſt them, and ſo delivering the <hi>Lower Rhine</hi> from the Chains that in time muſt have prov'd thoſe of the Empire.</p>
               <p>Sir, You have thus out-done the Enemy in Diligence, their moſt commendable Quality, if it were well imploy'd: You have overcome them, where they themſelves, and others too, think them moſt invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible, behind Walls: You have defeated their Troops, neither by num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber nor ſurprize; Advantages are to be taken; but it is greater not to ſtand in need of them.</p>
               <p>Thus your Highneſs hath begun the War, where it muſt end with Victory, and taken to your ſelf a ſhare in it ſuitable to the Dignity of your Family, and the importance of the Conjuncture, which gave your Highneſs the opportunity to Signalize the beginnings of your Regence by doing the publick ſuch eminent Services; as if Providence, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:30902:7"/>with the Integrity of your Intentions, took care, that no ſooner you ſhould be in a capacity to do good, but that the Publick ſhould require and receive the benefit of it, to ſignifie to your Highneſs, that the good of the Publick ought to be the end of your Greatneſs, and to others, That it is the end, and will be ſo.</p>
               <p>Sir, The great Power that God has put in your Hands, can at no Time be better imployed. Without Controverſie, the Peace and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of <hi>Europe,</hi> during this Age, depends upon the Succeſs of this War.</p>
               <p>All Laws, Divine and Humane, of Peace and War, the Fences of the publick Sufety are broke thorough; Thoſe eternal Dictates of Reaſon, the obligations of Honour, Humanity, Oaths, Promiſes, Religion, as well as the Cuſtoms of Nations, which the Neceſſities of Humane Affairs have rendred inviolable, and without which the great Society of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind can no more ſubſiſt, than privat Societies can without Rules and Laws: All theſe have been openly and avowedly trampled on.</p>
               <p>Now if the Ambition, and other Paſſions of Men that have done ſuch things, have carried them ſo far, notwithſtanding the juſt apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which, no doubt, they had of a general reſentment; whither will the ſame paſſions not carry them, if the preſent Confederacy ſhould hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to be fruſtrated, and there ſhould remain nothing more for them to be afraid of.</p>
               <p>But better things, no doubt, are reſerved for this Age. The Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot Wheels of thoſe that have asked Brick, and forbid Straw, begin already to move heavily. And provided the <hi>eaſterly</hi> Wind continue to blow ſteady, and neither little privat Intereſts, (ſure little in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon) nor certain points of Honour (only tolerable when Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent) diſorder the preſent Harmony, the event is infallible.</p>
               <p>Sir, Nothing can contribute more to this than the happy Union that is between the King my maſter, and your Electoral Highneſs, which ſtates His Majeſty, and your Highneſs, in the beſt Circumſtances ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable for preventing or removing differences.</p>
               <p>This, among other Reaſons, gives ground to hope, that the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracy is not to be broke, ſince the Union I ſpeak of cannot be diſſolv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. It is ſtrong, by all that is Sacred amongſt men, the Ties of Honour, Religion, Blood, Friendſhip, Obligations, Engagements, and I may add of the ſame Intereſts and Deſigns, with relation to the Publick.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:30902:7"/>
To ſo many Ties it may ſeem there needed no addition of a new one. But His Majeſty was reſolved not to loſe any opportunity of giving publick Inſtances of the great Affection and eſteem that he hath for your Electoral Highneſs: And the Knights Companions were unanimouſly of Opinion, That his Majeſty could not better diſpoſe of the greateſt Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour that he can give, than by ſending it to your Electoral Highneſs; from whom the Order may expect the greateſt return of Honour that it can at preſent receive.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="speech">
               <head>Monſieur <hi>FULCKS,</hi> Minister of State, His Speech.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
                  <p>
                     <hi>HIS moſt Serence Highneſs, the Elector of</hi> Brandenburg, <hi>our Gracious Prince, receives the Honour his Royal Majeſty of</hi> Great Britain <hi>has been pleaſed to confer on him, in ſending him the Badges of the moſt Noble Order of the Garter, with all due Reſpect and Eſteem. For whether its Antiquity be regarded, it being Three Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Thirty Nine Years ſince its firſt beginning, or the glorious Founder of it,</hi> Edward <hi>the Third, together with his Royal Qualities, eſpecially his unheard of Courage, and the Happineſs that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended him; or whether the Splendor and Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of thoſe that have been honour'd with the moſt Noble Order be conſidered; amongſt whom are reckon'd ſeveral great Monarchs, and what is wonderful, Eight Emperors, Five and Forty Kings, Sixty Electors and Princes, veſted with Soveraign Power, beſides a great many others</hi> Hero's <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned both by their Birth and Actions; or whether the deſign of the Inſtitution be looked on, which was the defence of Juſtice, the reliev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the oppreſſed, and the encouragement of true Vertue, 't will be found, that it gives place to no Order in the World, but on the contrary does far excel them all. The Excellency whereof is viſible, by thoſe two things that are abſolutely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in every true Knight, which are, not to have been tainted of any Baſeneſs, or of any Cowardize. But the Dignity of this Order his been ſo fully ſhewn by His Majeſties Envoy, that 'twold be ſuperfluous to add any thing to what
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:30902:8"/>he has ſaid. Indeed in the ancient Hiſtories of the</hi> Greeks <hi>and</hi> Romans, <hi>many Examples may be found, where Kingdoms and Provinces have been given away to others by the Poſſeſſors thereof; but Deſert and Right were not always the Cauſe of ſuch Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations. They were oftner made by blind Chance or Favour, or elſe Reaſons of State were the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of them. But that Honour which is found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded only on Merits, and which proceeds from a true and ſolid conſideration of Worth only, is to be preferred above Scepters and Crowns. And the conferring of this Noble Order muſt be thus looked upon, ſince it is done by a King who does nothing but with an exact knowledge and mature deliberation. For altho his Electoral Highneſs could not but have always thought it an Honour to have been of this Order, yet he looks upon it as greater ſtill in this, That the Dignity is conſerred upon him by his preſent Majeſty of</hi> Great Britain. <hi>The Diamonds and Gold which ſhine on the Badges thereof, receive yet a greater luſtre from ſo glorious a Hand, which the Divine Providence has made choice of to render this Age famous even for Miracles, to be a terror and chaſtiſment to Tyrants, to deliver the oppreſſed, raiſe up thoſe that were fallen, reſtore thoſe that are driven out, to ſtabliſh Tottering Crowns, and which having already freed Two Kingdoms, will in all probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity gloriouſly recover a Third in a ſhort time. Things that come from ſuch an auguſt hand can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be of excellent Vertue and Effect. His in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable Valour and Courage, and the bleſſing of Heaven, have had this great effect, that the moſt Famous Nations in the World, have put</hi> Four Crowns <hi>on his Head, and on that of his Royal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort, adorned likewiſe with all the ſame Vertues and Perfections. Which Crowns, in ſtead of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding any Ornament to the Perſons that are poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed of them, become more Illuſtrious from the heads of thoſe that wear them. His Electoral Highneſs was the firſt of any Forreign Prince that has received this Noble Token of Favour from His Royal Majeſty. From whence his Highneſs cannot but acknowledge, That tho His Royal Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and his Electoral Highneſs, were before nearly Related, His Royal Majeſty has thought fit to make ſtill a cloſer Union, 'Tis not to be queſtion'd but that it proceeds from the Secret Providence of God; That as this Order was inſtituted by</hi> Edward <hi>the Third, eſpecially againſt the</hi> French, <hi>who then, as at preſent, began to ſtrive for the Univerſal Monarchy, ſo now is conferr'd by</hi> Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam <hi>the Third, on</hi> Frederwick <hi>the Third, at a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:30902:8"/>time when they Two firſt of all diſplayed their Colours for the Freedom of</hi> Europe, <hi>and with U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited Forces, oppoſed Themſelves to that mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous and dreadful Enemy, rendring the Thing more Ominous, by the Badge which this Order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makes uſe of,</hi> Honi ſoit qui maly penſe. <hi>Let him periſh ſhamefully who dares raſhly deſpiſe this inſeparable Alliance. To this without doubt, His Royal Majeſty had regard, when He ſent the Sword to His Electoral Highneſs, which otherwiſe relates not to the Badges of the Order, and was never before conferred on any Knight; and with which he would have him girt with ſo great Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, that he might make uſe of it in his Wars, for the aſſerting the Freedom of</hi> Europe. <hi>His Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoral Highneſs certainly deſigns to do that which His Majeſty intended by conferring this Honour on him, and will always think himſelf ſo ſtrictly united to His Majeſty, that no Force nor Artifice ſhall ever be able to break the Union: But he will e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem whatever Fortune whether bad or good, that attends his Majeſty, to be the ſame as if it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd to his Highneſs, making no other difference betwixt his Majeſties Concerns and his own, than to give thoſe of his Majeſty the firſt place. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, his Electoral Highneſs will never render himſelf unworthy the Honour conferred, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get the Statutes of the Order. And becauſe his Electoral Highneſs is now become one of the Members of the Order, inſtituted amongſt the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Nation, his Highneſs will always endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to promote their Intereſt and Glory, Laſtly, His Highneſs thanks the Commiſſioners, in that they have been pleaſed to undertake the confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this Noble Preſent on him, and thanks his Royal Majeſty for having choſen them for this Solemnity, to whom his Electoral Highneſs will on all occaſions ſhew all Favour and Eſteem.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="lat" type="version">
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:30902:7"/>
                  <p>SEreniſſimus Princeps, Elector <hi>Brandenburgious,</hi> Dominus Noſter Clementiſſinus, debito cum reſpectu at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> aeſtimatione acceptat honorem, quo Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia Majeſtas Magnae Britanniae condecorare ipp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum voluit tranſmiſſis inſignibus toto Orbe cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bratiſſimi Ordinis Equitum Divi <hi>Georgli</hi> Anreae Periſcetidis. Sive enim reſpiciamus Antiquita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem inclytiſſimi Ordinis, qui jam trecentos trigin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta novem annos à primis ſuis incunabulis numerat; ſeu gloriam Fundatoris, <hi>Edvardi</hi> tertii, cum om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus to faſtigio dignis Virtutibus, tùm impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis inuſitatâ ſortitudine ac ſelicitate clariſſimi Regis; ſive Splendorem ac praeſtantiam corum queis iſtius Ordinis bonos obtigit, inter quos multi ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limes Monarchae, &amp; quod jamjam non ſine admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione audivimus, Octo Imperatores Romani, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draginta quin<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Reges, Sexaginta Electores, &amp; ut plurimùm Supremo Imperio gaudentes Principes, praeter plurimos alios non minus Splendore Nataeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, quàm rerum geſtarum gloria celeberrimos He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roes numerantur; ſive etiam ſcopum inſtituti qui praecipnè ad deſenſionem Juſtitiae, ſublevationem oppreſſorum, &amp; cultum virae at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> infucatae Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutis tendit; manifeſſò deprehendetur, iſthune nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li alteri ejus generis Ordini toto Orbe concedere, multis autem rebus alios longe antecellere. Cujus praeſtantiae infallibile documentum perſpicitur in duobus palmariis genuini Equitis requiſitis, ut quod turpiſugâ tergum hoſti obverterit, infi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti potuerit. Sed quae ad dignitatem kujus Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:30902:8"/>ſpectant, ea jam à Domino Legato itae lucu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenter ac ſolide deducta ſunt, ut ſuperfluum ſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit eidem aliquid ſuperaddere velle. Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem in Antiquâ Hiſtoria <hi>Graecorum</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primis &amp; <hi>Romanorum</hi> multa licet videre Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pla. Regnorum ac inſignium Provinciarum à Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſoribus in alios collatorum. Sed tantorum mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerum cauſa non ſemper meritum ant jus reperitur: Saepe iſta caeca fortuna, aut enormi favori deben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nur, aut quia Reipublicae rationes ïſta per alios potius poſſideri ſuaſerunt. Ast qui ſolo Virtutis merito utitur, &amp; ex verâ ſolidâque praeſtantiae aeſtimatione promanet honos ipſisSceptris Core<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſque longè praeſtabilior habendus. Atque eodem modulo quoque collatio inclyti hujus Ordinis menſuranda eſt, imprimis cum ea proficiſcatur à Rege, cui nil niſi praeviâ exacta cognitione &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turo judicio ſuſcipitur. Quanquem enim Sereni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas ſua Electoralis ſemper ſibi decorum babitura fuerat illuſtriſſime huie Ordini adſcrib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Quod tamen id à Regiâ Majeſtate Magnae Britanniae, quae nunc rerum potitur, fiat, id multis modis gaudium, quo ipſius mens ex tá-perfunditur, adau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get. Quin ipſi Adamantes &amp; Aurum, qutis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignia Ordinis radiant, multò vividiorem Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorem mutuantur à manu tam glorioſi collatoris, quam Manum Divina Providentia elegit ad Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum hoc Miraculis inſigniendum, quae Tyrannis Terrorem incutit, torumque inſolentiam caſtigat &amp; ſolo affligit, quae Oppreſsos liberat, &amp; è rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis ſublevat, ſpoliatos <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſtituit, titubantes Core<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas ſtabilit, immo quae adhuc calet ab admiran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da liberatione duorum Regnorum, cui &amp; de ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio propediem trophaeum ſtatuendum Auguramur. Quae à tam Augustâ menu dantu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſingulari Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute &amp; effectu vacua eſse non poſſunt velut quae incomparabili ſuâ fortitudine animique conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiâ, ac coelitùs proſperate ſucceſſu effecit, ut ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leberrima toto orbe Natio quatuor Coronas ipſins &amp; ſereniſſimae Conſortis Reginae, omnium Virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ac gratiarum Matris, capiti exornando por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rexerit: Quibus Corenis tamen divinum Lumen quo caput iſind circumſunditur, plus ſplendoris af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fert quam ab iiſdem Accipit. Quo &amp; illud Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedit, quod ſerenitas ſua Electoralis inter exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos Principes prima fit, quam Regia ſua Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtas illuſtri bocce aeſtimationis ac benevolentiae ſua ſigno muneravit. Ex quo &amp; eadem agnoſcit, quòd licet jam antea Regia ſua Majeſtas &amp; ſere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitas ſua Electoralis ſanctiſſimo ſanguinis &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinquae cognationis vinculo divinitùs ſint com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binaiae, Regiae tamen Majestas iſthane neceſſitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem iſthoc ordinis ligamine arctius adbue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtringere praeclarum duxerit.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:30902:8"/>Nec dubitare fas est, quin &amp; iſtud ex occultâ operations Divinae providentiae promanâ it, ut cùm bie Ordo primum ab Edvardo tertio inſtitutus fuerit, &amp; quidem praecipuè contra Gallos, qui jam tum inſolentiam &amp; dominands libidinem, quâ nunc totum foè Orbem ſubverſum eunt, parturithant, idim nunc à Guiliclmo tertio in Fridericum tertium confera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp; to quidem tempore, quo bi duo primi ſignum ad excutiendum, quod Europae cervicibus imminebar, jugum fuſtulerunt, ac junctis animis viribuſque immani ac truculento iſti hoſti ſeſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecerunt, anſpicatiſſimis victoriarum monumentis ſimboli, quô bic ordo utitur, Omen firmaturi, <hi>Hony ſolt qui mal y penſe,</hi> dedecore obrutus pereat, qui inſolubilem hanc conjunctionem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temnere, aut temerare Awus ſuerit. Quò e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam, ſine dubio, proſolitâ ſibi Sapientiâ, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpexit Regia Sacra Majeſtas, cùm Serenttati ſuae Electorali Gladium, qui aliàs cum Ordinis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignibus tranſmitti non ſolet. <hi>Ad inſignia Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diois haud ſpectat,</hi> &amp; antea nemini Equitum oblatus fuit, Offerri, todem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> illam in tantâ Solennitate accingi juſſerit; ut nimirum eadem in Belli &amp; Periculorum Societate; ad afferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam Europae Libertatem à jugo <hi>Gallico</hi> utere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Sanè Serenitas ſua Electoralis Regia Suae Majeſtatis ſcopum, ad quem delato hocce Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nore collimat, ex aſse implebit. Eadem its ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctè Regiae ſuae Majeſtati ſeſe obſtrictam judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit, ut nulla vis aut fraus ad eam divellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam valitura fit: Quaecun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Regiae Sua Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtati, proſpere aut ſecùs eveneriut, ſibi quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que accidiſse judicabit. Deni<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Regiaeſuae Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jestatis &amp; proprias rationes non alio diſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine habebit, quam quod iſtis exra priorque locus deforendus ſit. De caesero, Serenitas ſua Electoralis delato bocce. Honore nunquam ſeſe indignum reddet, ac Statuta Ordinis Memori ſemper mente tenebit. Et quia Serenitas ſua Electoralis nunc inter Membra Ordinis recepta eſt, ab intlytâ Natione <hi>Anglicana</hi> inſtituti, bujus Gloria &amp; Emolumentum eidem ſemper quam maxime cordi trunt: Ad Extremum Serenitas ſua Electoralis Dominis Legatis Gratias agit, quod officium tam egregii &amp; acceptiſſimi Muneris offerendi in ſe ſuſcipere voluerunt: Eidem gratiſſimum eſt à ſuà Regia Majeſtatá iſtos potiſſimùm huic Functioni obeundae delectos, quos &amp; quâ Aeſtimatione &amp; Affectu Sua Serenitas Electoralis proſequatur, nulla occaſione demonſtrare omittet.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:30902:9"/>
            <p>LICENS'D</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>G. SAR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M.</hi> Chancellor of the Order.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>July</hi> 15.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed at <hi>London,</hi> and Re-Printed at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> by the Heir of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew Anderſon,</hi> Printer to Their moſt Excellent Majeſties, 1690.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:30902:9"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
